<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>DNS Security (DNSSEC) helps protect against DNS-spoofing attacks by
    providing origin authentication and integrity protection of DNS
    information. Proper maintenance of a DNSSEC-enhanced DNS zone is essential
    to protecting the domain's zone data.</para>

    <para>This Step-by-Step DNSSEC-Tools Operator Guidance Document is
    intended for operations using the DNSSEC-Tools v0.2 distribution. It will
    assist operators in gaining operational experience with DNSSEC. Some basic
    understanding of DNSSEC terms and concepts is required. It follows the
    format laid out by <xref linkend="dnssec-operators-guide" />.</para>

    <para>This document is meant to be a learning aid and is not intended to
    define policy in any form. Any implicit recommendations for key sizes,
    signature validity periods, and command line parameters are for
    illustration purposes ONLY and MUST NOT be used in production environments
    unless due-diligence has been taken to ensure that these values are
    acceptable within such environments. See <xref
    linkend="dnssec-operational-practices" /> for suggestions on determining
    appropriate security characteristics.</para>

    <para>This document was written as part of the DNSSEC-Tools project. The
    goal of this project is to create a set of documentation, tools, patches,
    applications, libraries, wrappers, extensions, and plug-ins that will help
    ease the deployment of DNSSEC-related technologies. For more information
    about this project and the tools that are being developed and provided,
    please see the DNSSEC-Tools project web page at:
    <uri>http://www.dnssec-tools.org</uri>.</para>

    <section id="intro-organization">
        <title>Organization of this Document</title>

        <para>The following operations are described in this document:</para>

        <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Key Concepts</title>

        <para>A number of concepts must be known in order to understand this
        document.</para>

        <section>
            <title>Key-Tag Tables</title>

            <para>The Key-Tag Table mentioned in several steps is a record of
            zones, the zone's keys, attributes of the keys, and expiration
            dates. This may be kept in any usable form -- computer file,
            notebook, old paper napkin, or whatever</para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="intro-conventions">
        <title>Conventions Used in this Document</title>

        <para>One of the goals of this document is to self-contain DNS
        Security operations within sections and prevent constant
        cross-referencing between sections. Consequently, certain parts of the
        text are repeated throughout the document.</para>

        <para>Text marked in bold represents text or commands entered by users
        within a given procedural step.</para>

        <para>Underlined text, which can also be bold, is a place-holder for
        actual run-time values. These values are either automatically
        generated or are values that are known to the user from some other
        step.</para>

        <para>Additionally, the following typographical conventions are used
        in this document.</para>

        <table colsep="0" frame="none" rowsep="0">
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <application>command</application>
                        </entry>

                        <entry>Command names</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <filename>filename</filename>
                        </entry>

                        <entry>File and path names</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <uri>URL</uri>
                        </entry>

                        <entry>Web URLs</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <command>execution</command>
                        </entry>

                        <entry>Simple command executions</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

        <para>Longer sets of command sequences are given in this
        format:</para>

        <simplelist>
            <member><prompt>$</prompt> <command>cd /tmp</command>
            <userinput>[ENTER]</userinput></member>

            <member><prompt>$</prompt> <command>ls</command>
            <userinput>[ENTER]</userinput></member>

            <member><prompt>$</prompt> <command>rm -fr *</command>
            <userinput>[ENTER]</userinput></member>

            <member><prompt>$</prompt></member>
        </simplelist>

        <para>In most cases, output will not be displayed for given command
        sequences.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="intro-acknowledgements">
        <title>Acknowledgments</title>

        <para>This document builds upon the procedures laid out in <xref
        linkend="dnssec-operators-guide" />.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="intro-comments">
        <title>Comments</title>

        <para>Please send any comments and corrections to
        developers@dnssec-tools.org.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
