<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>DNS Security (DNSSEC) helps protect against DNS-spoofing attacks by
    providing origin authentication and integrity protection of DNS
    information. Proper maintenance of a DNSSEC-enhanced DNS zone is essential
    to protecting the domain's zone data.</para>

    <para>This Step-by-Step DNSSEC-Tools Operator Guidance Document is
    intended for operations using the DNSSEC-Tools v0.2 distribution. It will
    assist operators in gaining operational experience with DNSSEC. Some basic
    understanding of DNSSEC terms and concepts is required. It follows the
    format laid out by <xref linkend="dnssec-operators-guide" />.</para>

    <para>This document is meant to be a learning aid and is not intended to
    define policy in any form. Any implicit recommendations for key sizes,
    signature validity periods, and command line parameters are for
    illustration purposes ONLY and MUST NOT be used in production environments
    unless due-diligence has been taken to ensure that these values are
    acceptable within such environments. See <xref
    linkend="dnssec-operational-practices" /> for suggestions on determining
    appropriate security characteristics.</para>

    <para>This document was written as part of the DNSSEC-Tools project. The
    goal of this project is to create a set of documentation, tools, patches,
    applications, libraries, wrappers, extensions, and plug-ins that will help
    ease the deployment of DNSSEC-related technologies. For more information
    about this project and the tools that are being developed and provided,
    please see the DNSSEC-Tools project web page at:
    <uri>http://www.dnssec-tools.org</uri>.</para>

    <section id="intro-organization">
        <title>Organization of this Document</title>

        <para>This guide contains the following sections.</para>

        <para>Chapter 1. Introduction to the Step-By-Step Guide.</para>

        <para>Chapter 2. Describes the configuration required before the
        DNSSEC-Tools utilities may be used.</para>

        <para>Chapter 3. Describes how to perform an initial signing of a
        zone.</para>

        <para>Chapter 4. Provides the steps required to configure a name
        server to serve a signed zone.</para>

        <para>Chapter 5. Gives information on checking for expiration of a
        zone's signatures.</para>

        <para>Chapter 6. Describes how to re-sign a previously signed
        zone.</para>

        <para>Chapter 7. Provides the commands required for a child zone to
        create a signed delegation.</para>

        <para>Chapter 8. Gives the commands required for a parent zone to
        create a signed delegation.</para>

        <para>Chapter 9. Describes the Pre-Publish Scheme, which is used in
        rollover operations of ZSK keys.</para>

        <para>Chapter 10. Provides the Double-Signature Scheme, which is used
        in rollover operations of KSK keys.</para>

        <para>Chapter 11. Gives the emergency rollover procedures to take in
        the event of a ZSK key compromise.</para>

        <para>Chapter 12. Describes the emergency rollover procedures to take
        in the event of a Published ZSK key compromise.</para>

        <para>Chapter 13. Provides the emergency rollover procedures to take
        in the event that both the Published and Current ZSK keys are
        compromised.</para>

        <para>Chapter 14. Gives the emergency rollover procedures to take if
        the KSK key is compromised.</para>

        <para>Chapter 15. Describes the actions a parent zone must take when a
        child zone's KSK key is compromised.</para>

        <para>Chapter 16. Provides a migration path for moving to using the
        DNSSEC-Tools toolset.</para>

        <para>Chapter 17. Gives information on configuring a secure
        resolver.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Key Concepts</title>

        <para>A number of concepts must be known in order to understand this
        document.</para>

        <section>
            <title>Zones and Encryption Keys</title>

            <para>Zones and Encryption Keys are essential for understanding
            this document, but they are also beyond its scope.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Zone Rollover</title>

            <para>As zone signatures expire, the zone must be re-signed with
            new encryption keys. The process of generating new encryption keys
            and re-signing the zone is called <emphasis>zone
            rollover</emphasis>. There are several rollover schemes (e.g.,
            Double-Signature Scheme and Pre-Publish Scheme) that are used for
            various purposes. These schemes are described in Sections ??? and
            ???.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Key-Tag Tables</title>

            <para>The Key-Tag Table is a record of zones, the zone's keys,
            attributes of the keys, and expiration dates. This may be kept in
            any usable form -- computer file, notebook, old paper napkin, or
            whatever</para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Keyrec Files</title>

            <para>Keyrec files function as Key-Tag Tables for DNSSEC-Tools
            utilities. They can be hand-edited, but the DNSSEC-Tools update
            them automatically.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Rollrec Files</title>

            <para>Rollrec files contain information needed by the DNSSEC-Tools
            key rollovers. They can be hand-edited, but the DNSSEC-Tools
            update them automatically.</para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="intro-conventions">
        <title>Conventions Used in this Document</title>

        <para>One of the goals of this document is to self-contain DNS
        Security operations within sections and prevent constant
        cross-referencing between sections. Consequently, certain parts of the
        text are repeated throughout the document.</para>

        <para>Text marked in bold represents text or commands entered by users
        within a given procedural step.</para>

        <para>Underlined text, which can also be bold, is a place-holder for
        actual run-time values. These values are either automatically
        generated or are values that are known to the user from some other
        step.</para>

        <para>Additionally, the following typographical conventions are used
        in this document.</para>

        <table colsep="0" frame="none" rowsep="0">
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <application>command</application>
                        </entry>

                        <entry>Command names</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <filename>filename</filename>
                        </entry>

                        <entry>File and path names</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <uri>URL</uri>
                        </entry>

                        <entry>Web URLs</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <command>execution</command>
                        </entry>

                        <entry>Simple command executions</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

        <para>Longer sets of command sequences are given in this
        format:</para>

        <simplelist>
            <member><command># cd /tmp</command>
            <userinput>[ENTER]</userinput></member>

            <member><command># ls</command>
            <userinput>[ENTER]ijc</userinput></member>

            <member><command># rm -fr *</command>
            <userinput>[ENTER]</userinput></member>

            <member><command>#</command></member>
        </simplelist>

        <para>In most cases, output will not be displayed for given command
        sequences.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="intro-acknowledgments">
        <title>Acknowledgments</title>

        <para>This document builds upon the procedures laid out in <xref
        linkend="dnssec-operators-guide" />.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="intro-comments">
        <title>Comments</title>

        <para>Please send any comments and corrections to
        sparta-dnssec@tislabs.com.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>